翻译：潇湘月影  wyk8818  小英的小号
翻译：吃货丁小七  彼岸荼蘼
校对：somehacker
总监：somehacker
后期：bongpong
幸福终点站
联合航空公司
United Airlines announcing
从北京来的9435号班机已经到达
the arrival of Flight 9435 from Beijing.
旅客服务代表  请到C42门报到
Customer service representative, report to Gate C42.
前往美国的旅客请在1至15号柜台排队
All visitors to the US should line up at booths one to 15.
请填写好入境表格
Please have your I-94 forms filled out.
您此行的目的是什么
What's the purpose of your visit?
您此行的目的是什么  公差还是私事
What is the purpose of your visit? Business or pleasure?
就是观光  购物
Just visiting. Shopping?
私事
Euh, plaisir.
-私事  -公差
- Pleasure. - Business.
您打算在美国逗留多久
How long will you be staying in United States?
能出示一下您的回程机票吗
Could I see your return ticket?
-您此行的目的是什么  -公差还是私事
- What's the purpose of your visit? - Business or pleasure?
-私事  -祝您此行愉快  下一位
- Pleasure. - Enjoy your stay. Next.
请准备好护照  移民申请表  入境申请表I-94
Please have your passports, immigration forms I-94
以及入关申报表等待核查
and customs declaration ready to hand to the inspector.
-准备  他在搜索  -收到
- Stand by. He's fishing. - Copy that.
看见那群穿米老鼠运动衫的人了吗
See this bunch of Mickey Mouse sweatshirts standing here?
那是中国来的旅行团  要去奥兰多
That's the tour from China, connecting to Orlando.
为什么一群中国游客
When was the last time you saw a group of Chinese tourists
去迪士尼却不带照相机
on their way to Disney World not a single one of them had a camera?
10号11号柜台可能有人伪造证件
Possible forged documents on 10 and 11.
先生  先生  护照
Sir. Sir. Passport.
谢谢
Thank you.
欢迎  纳沃斯基先生
Welcome, Mr. Navorski.
您此行的目的是什么
Purpose of your visit?
国际护照有效
扫描识别
公差还是私事
Business or pleasure?
移除文件
请准备好入关申报表
Have your declarations forms ready, please.
国际护照失效
长官  6号柜台检索系统出问题了
Sir, I have an IBIS hit on six.
纳沃斯基先生  请跟我来
Mr. Navorski, please follow me.
搭乘蒙特利尔飞来的746号航班的旅客
flight number 746 from Montreal
认领行李前请先去移民登记处
must proceed to U.S. Immigration before claiming their luggage.
纳沃斯基先生  请在这里等一下
All right, Mr. Navorski, we'd like you to wait here, please.
下一位
Next, please.
您来美国究竟有何目的  纳沃斯基先生
What exactly are you doing in the United States, Mr. Navorski?
请帮我叫黄色出租车
Yellow taxicab, please.
我要去华美达酒店
Take me to Ramada Inn,
莱克星顿路  161号
161 Lexington.
您要入住华美达酒店吗
Staying at the Ramada Inn?
不用找零了
Keep the change.
您在纽约有认识的人吗
Do you know anyone here in New York?
是的
Yes.
-谁  -是的
- Who? - Yes.
-不是  您在纽约有认识的人吗  -是的
- No, do you know anyone in New York? - Yes.
-谁  -是的
- Who? - Yes.
莱克星顿路  161号
161 Lexington.
好吧  纳沃斯基先生
Okay, Mr. Navorski,
请给我看看您的回程机票
I'm gonna need to see your return ticket, please.
不  您的回程机票
No, your return ticket.
对
Yes.
这只是标准程序
This is just a standard procedure.
我还需要您的护照
I'm going to need the passport also.
好
Oh. Oh, okay.
-不  不   -谢谢
- No, no. - Thank you.
不  纳沃斯基先生
No, Mr. Navorski.
那个  护照
That. Passport.
那个
That.
纳沃斯基先生  抱歉久等了
Mr. Navorski? Sorry to keep you waiting.
我是弗兰克·迪克逊
I'm Frank Dixon,
肯尼迪国际机场海关及边境保卫局主任
Director of Customs and Border Protection here at JFK.
也就是说  我负责处理移民相关问题
Which means that I help people with their immigration problems.
我们正在帮您找翻译
We're looking for an interpreter for you.
怎么样了  找到翻译了吗
How are we doing on that? Do we have an interpreter?
好吧  我知道您会说一点英语
Ok. But I understand that you speak a little English.
-是  -您会说对吧
- Yes. - You do?
-是  -很好
- Yes. - Good.
希望您不介意我边吃边谈
I hope you don't mind if I eat while we talk.
我有些坏消息
I've a bit of bad news.
您的护照上  政府赋予您的所有权利
It seems that your country has suspended all traveling privileges
现在都被您的国家收回了
on passports that have been issued by your government.
我国国务院撤销了您的签证
And our State Department has revoked the visa
您不可以进入美国
that was going to allow you to enter the U.S.
简单来说  基本就是这样
That's it in a nutshell, basically.
您在飞机上的时候
Anyway, it seems that while you were in the air,
您的国家似乎发生了军事政变
there was a military coup in your country.
死者大多是总统卫队成员
Most of the dead were members of the Presidential Guard.
他们半夜受袭  发生了猛烈交火
They were attacked in the middle of the night. There's a terrible fire fight.
电视上应该播过了
They got it all on GHN, I think.
平民伤亡很少  您的家人应该没事
There were few civilian casualties. I'm sure your family's fine.
纳沃斯基先生  您的国家发生了内乱
Mr. Navorski, your country was annexed from the inside.
卡科吉亚共和国更换了领导人
The Republic of Krakozhia is under new leadership.
卡科吉亚  卡科吉亚
Krakozhia! Krakozhia.
-卡科吉亚  -好吧  我觉得他没听懂
- Krakozhia. - Right. I don't think he gets it.
让我...好吧  你看
Let me...OK, look.
假设这包薯片是卡科基亚
Imagine that these potato chips are Krakozhia.
-卡科吉亚  -卡科吉亚
- Krakozhia. - Krakozhia.
-对  很好  -卡科吉亚
- Yes. Okay. - Krakozhia.
这包薯片是卡科吉亚
So the potato chips are Krakozhia.
-这个苹果...  -大苹果[纽约]
- And this apple... - Big Apple.
大苹果代表叛乱分子  好吗
Big Apple represents the Liberty Rebels. Okay?
没有卡科吉亚了  懂吗
No more Krakozhia. Okay?
新政府  革命  你懂吗
New government. Revolution. You understand?
出入你们国家的航班都无限期顺延了
All the flights in and out of your country have been suspended indefinitely.
新政府封锁了边境
The new government has sealed all borders,
也就是说您的护照和签证失效了
which means that your passport and visa's no longer valid.
目前而言  您不属于任何一个国家
So, currently, you are a citizen of nowhere.
即使我们能为您更换新文件
Now, even if we could get you new papers
也没法给您签发
we couldn't process them
直到美国政府为您的国家进行外交重分类
until the U.S. recognizes your country's new diplomatic reclassification.
您不享有庇护权  难民身份
You don't qualify for asylum, refugee status,
临时保护身份  人道主义入境许可
temporary protective status, humanitarian parole
或是非移民工作  旅游  外交签证
or non-immigration work travel or diplomatic visa.
这些您都不能享受
You don't qualify for any of these things.
您现在...
You are at this time simply...
-被拒绝了  -被拒绝了
- unacceptable. - Unacceptable.
- Unacceptable. - Unacceptable.
纽约游包括布鲁克林大桥
Big Apple tour includes Brooklyn Bridge,
帝国大厦  百老汇音乐剧《猫》
Empire State, Broadway show Cats.
还有个坏消息要告诉您  纳沃斯基先生
I got more bad news for you, Mr. Navorski.
《猫》已经停演了
Cats has closed.
好吧  好吧
Okay. Okay.
那我去纽约了  谢谢
Now I go New York City. Thank you.
不  纳沃斯基先生
No, Mr. Navorski.
我现在不能让您进入美国国境
I cannot allow you to enter the United States at this time.
-卡科吉亚  -我们也不能让您回国
- Krakozhia. - We can't allow you to go home either.
您也没有祖国了
The thing is you don't really have a home.
严格来说  它不存在了
Technically, it doesn't exist.
就像是《阴阳魔界》一样
It's like a Twilight Zone.
-您看过那部剧吗  -对
- Do you ever see that show? - Yes.
-你们那里播过吗  -对
- Do you get that show over there? - Yes.
"多嘴的蒂娜"
"Talking Tina,"
"三万英尺噩梦"
"Nightmare at 30,000 Feet,"
"赞提星超能者"
"Zanti Misfits."
"赞提星超能者"是《外星限界》里的  长官
"Zanti Misfits" Was Outer Limits, sir.
是吗  这不重要
Oh, really? It's not important.
我该上哪买耐克鞋
Where do I buy the Nike shoes?
纳沃斯基先生  过来  跟我来
Okay, Mr. Navorski, come here. Walk with me.
我也很为难  纳沃斯基先生
Here's my dilemma, Mr. Navorski.
您无权进入美国
You have no legal right to enter the U.S.
我也无权拘押你
And I have no legal right to detain you.
您就像是掉入了现行制度的小漏洞里
It seems that you have fallen through a small crack in the system.
-我是漏洞[神经病]  -对  在这个问题解决之前
- I am crack. - Yes. Until we get this sorted out,
我只能允许您进入国际中转候机厅
I have no choice but to allow you to enter the International Transit Lounge.
我会签署一张授权协议书
I'm going to sign a release form
让您能够自由出入
that is going to make you a free man.
-自由  -自由
- Free? - Free.
在国际中转候机厅范围内
Free to go anywhere you like
你想去哪里都可以
within the confines of the International Transit Lounge.
-好吗  -好
- Okay? - Okay
-好吧  -好
好
Okay.
估计明天政府就能把这事解决
I'm sure that Uncle Sam will have this sorted out by tomorrow,
欢迎来到美国  虽然差一点
and welcome to the United States. Almost.
-谢谢你  -谢了  乔奇
- Thank you. - Thanks, Judge.
美国国土安全部
纳沃斯基先生
Now, Mr. Navorski.
Mr. Navorski.
纳沃斯基先生
这里是国际中转候机厅
This is the International Transit Lounge.
您可以在这里随意等候  这些是餐券
You are free to wait here. These are food vouchers.
您可以在楼上餐饮区使用
You can use them up in the Food Court.
您的卡科吉亚钱在这儿用不了
Your Krakozhian money is no good here.
这是一张预付15分钟的电话卡
This is a 15-minute, prepaid calling card.
您可以给家里打电话
You may call home, if you like.
这是一个传呼机  方便我们联络您
This, in case we need to contact you, is a pager.
请务必随身携带
You must keep this with you at all times.
这张身份卡能让您出入海关与边防局
Here is an ID badge for you to get into CBP.
那几扇门后...
Beyond those doors...
纳沃斯基先生  请看着我
Mr. Navorski. I'm going to need you to look at me.
那几扇门后就是美国领土
Beyond those doors is American soil.
迪克逊先生要我跟你说清楚
Mr. Dixon wants me to make it very clear to you
您不能穿过那几扇门
that you are not to enter through those doors.
您不能离开这栋建筑  美国对您关闭了
You are not to leave this building. America is closed.
美国关闭了
America closed.
那我做什么
What I do?
在这儿只能做一件事  纳沃斯基先生
There's only one thing you can do here, Mr. Navorski.
购物
Shop.
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
搭乘854号航班从纽约前往华沙的旅客...
passengers of flight 854 New York to Warsaw...
国际社会正试图和平解决争端
The international community tries to make inroads to a peaceful resolution.
与此同时  民众不禁疑惑
Meanwhile, the populace has to wonder
政治局面能否稳定下来
if they will ever find political stability,
他们的领导人能否在国际舞台上站稳脚跟
or find the leadership to secure their place on the world stage.
接下来  想买一艘90英尺的游艇吗
And next this hour, looking to buy a 90-foot yacht?
被劫为人质
...have been taken hostage.
有消息称  副总统和4名内阁成员
We're also hearing that the Vice President has been killed along with four cabinet members,
13名受伤士兵以及20位平民被杀
13 injured soldiers and 20 civilians.
黎明时候  叛军领导人包围了议会大楼
By dawn, rebel leaders had surrounded the state houses.
为了宣布政权交替  总统官邸和国会大楼的
In a symbolic gesture, the national flag of Krakozhia was torn down
卡科吉亚国旗已被撤下
from the Presidential Palace and the parliament building.
帮帮忙  帮帮忙
Please. Please.
电视
Television.
外事局刚刚发来消息
This just in from our overseas bureau.
昨晚  一场军事政变推翻了卡科吉亚政府
Last night a military coup overthrew the government of Krakozhia.
爆炸和枪声彻夜不停
Bombing and gunfire were heard through the night.
虽然政变细节尚不明晰
Although details of the coup are unclear,
有消息称
we are told that President
瓦格巴金总统及其副官已被劫为人质
Vagobagin and his aides have been taken hostage.
您好  先生  您是红毯俱乐部的会员吗
Bonjour, monsieur. You are a Red Carpet Club member?
请您出示登机牌和会员卡  先生
I need to see your boarding pass and club card, sir.
抱歉  先生  这里是私人候机室
I'm sorry, sir. This is a private lounge.
公共候机室在楼下
The public lounge is downstairs.
该地区最小的国家
The tiniest nation in the region
又一次发生叛乱
has been shaken by another uprising.
卡科吉亚在80年代末和90年代
Krakozhia has been involved in civil war throughout the late '80s and '90s
卡科吉亚危机
从共产主义转型过程中一直内战不断
as it has tried to transition from Communist rule.
-小心点  -帮帮忙
- Watch it. - Please.
帮帮忙  电话  电话
Please, telephone? Telephone?
帮帮忙  帮帮忙
Please, please.
出于安全考虑
For security reasons,
请将您的行李随身携带
please keep your luggage with you at all times.
无人看管的行李将被拖走送检甚至销毁
Unattended luggage will be removed for inspection and maybe destroyed.
天啊  天啊  你压坏了我的箱子
Oh, my God. Oh, my God, you broke my bag!
这是我在巴黎买的  我最喜欢它了
I got this in Paris. This is my favorite bag.
你居然把我的箱子压坏了
I can't believe you just broke my bag.
爸妈  他把我的箱子压坏了
Mom, Dad. He broke my bag.
-食物文件  -抱歉  住手
- Food document. - Excuse me. Stop it.
你有预约吗
Do you have an appointment?
抱歉
I'm sorry,
没有预约我不允许任何人翻检我的垃圾
I don't let anyone to look at my trash without an appointment.
-下个星期二是垃圾开放日  -星期二
- I have an opening next Tuesday. - Tuesday.
星期一  星期二  星期三  星期二
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Tuesday.
到时您可以回来寻找失物
It will be good time for you to come back and get lost.
好了  再见  抱歉
Okay, goodbye. Sorry.
星期二
Tuesday.
别开枪
Don't shoot.
她能容纳12个人  弗兰克
She sleeps 12, Frank.
船上有120伏特的发电机  吧台  煤气灶
Has a 120-volt generator, wet bar, gas range.
太迷人了
She looks amazing.
她是我的梦想  弗兰克  我的梦中情人
She's my dream, Frank. My pot of gold at the end of the rainbow.
这艘船漂亮极了  祝您早日梦想成真
She's a beautiful boat, and I hope you get her soon.
-这是您应得的  -谢谢  弗兰克
- You've earned her. - Thank you, Frank.
-说真的  -其实我昨天就买下来了
- You have. - Actually, I bought her yesterday.
天啊  恭喜您
Oh, come on. Congratulations.
弗兰克  我要推荐你接我的班
Frank, I'm nominating you to take my place.
从今天起  你开始履行外勤专员的责任
Starting today, you will assume the duties of acting Field Commissioner
就等政府正式委任了
until you get approval from Washington.
真的吗  我都不知道该说什么了
Really? I don't know what to say.
-天啊  真的吗  理查德  -是真的  弗兰克
- Jesus. Richard, is this real? - Oh, it's real, Frank.
别假装挺吃惊的了
Don't you stand there pretending to be surprised.
你肯定早盼着我退休或是进棺材呢
You've been waiting for me to retire or drop dead for years now.
我可没盼着您退休
No, I haven't been waiting for you to retire.
没事  弗兰克
That's all right, Frank.
等你宣誓就职我就退休
My retirement will become official the day you get sworn in.
-你盼着这一天好久了  -是啊
- You've waited a long time for this. - I have.
上边来审查的时候小心点
Just be careful about the inspection process.
我会的  我在这干了17年了
I will. I've been here for 17 years...
弗兰克  这可是外勤专员的位子
Frank, we're talking about the Field Commissioner position.
大家会唯你马首是瞻
People are going to look to you for leadership,
你要树立好榜样
to set an example.
您想说什么
What are you saying?
好好干  别砸了饭碗
I'm saying the job is yours to lose.
把哥伦比亚人送去参加避难听证会
Ship the Colombians off to asylum hearings,
中国人遣返前先调查前科和背景
run priors and backgrounds on the Chinese before deporting.
打电话给长岛的孩子们的家长
And call the parents of those kids from Long Island,
告诉他们不该让小孩去牙买加
tell them it was a bad idea to let them go to Jamaica.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
好了大伙儿  动起来
Come on, everybody, let's go.
南美和马德里的航班刚降落
We got South America and Madrid on the tarmac.
半小时内完成旅客过关  快点
I want them out of here in half an hour. Come on.
瑟曼先生
Mr. Thurman.
有个穿睡衣的家伙在航站楼里晃悠
There's a man walking around the terminal in a bathrobe.
我知道  长官  是您让他待在那儿的
I know, sir. You put him there.
准许入境
下一位
Next.
我需要签证
I need visa.
您的绿色表格呢
Where's your green form?
没有绿色入境表格我没法给您办理
I can't do anything without your green entry form.
去墙那边领
Go to the wall.
下一位
Next!
先生
Sir.
是浅绿色的表格
The light green form.
我爱纽约
I love New York...
浅绿色
Light green.
-纳沃斯基先生  -怎么了
- Mr. Navorski, - Yes.
没有签证您就进不了纽约
you cannot get into New York without a visa.
没有护照就办不了签证
You cannot get a visa without a passport,
而没有国家就拿不了新护照
and you cannot get a new passport without a country.
我们对此无能为力
There's nothing we can do for you here.
我给你浅绿色表格了
I give you light green.
我很抱歉  但您浪费了一整天
I'm sorry, but you've wasted an entire day.
现在  您只能被...
At this time, you are simply...
-被拒绝了  -对
- Unacceptable. - Yes.
被拒绝了
Unacceptable.
拒绝入境
他怎么还在这儿
Why is he still here?
您把他释放了  长官
You released him, sir.
是您让他待在那儿的
You put him there.
他怎么不走呢  怎么不逃跑呢
Why doesn't he walk out the doors? Why doesn't he try to escape?
长官  您让他等着
Sir, you told him to wait.
我没想到他真会等
I didn't think he'd actually do it.
他钻了漏洞出不来了  谁愿意等下去啊
I mean, he's in a crack. Who the hell waits in a crack?
国务院还是没消息
No news from the State Department,
也许过几天就可以将他遣返了
but I think we can deport him in a few days.
可能是几天
Yeah, it could be a few days.
也可能是一周  两周  一个月
It could be a week, two weeks, a month.
天知道他是怎么想的
Who knows what this guy is thinking,
他是从集中营逃出来的吗
what gulag he escaped from.
他的一举一动都要向我汇报
Everything he does comes back to me.
您要把他关回拘留室吗
You want to bring him back in the holding cell?
不  我要放他出去
No, I'll show him the door.
你好
Hello.
-有预约吗  -有的  九点半
- Do you have an appointment? - Yes. 9:30.
食物文件  垃圾  星期二
Food document, trash. Tuesday.
星期二  我讨厌星期二
Tuesday. I hate the Tuesday.
借过
Excuse me.
机场是个有意思的地方  纳沃斯基先生
Airports are tricky places, Mr. Navorski.
我有些事要告诉你
I'm about to tell you something.
你不能告诉别人
Something you can never repeat to anyone.
明白吗  这是秘密
Do you understand? It's a secret.
-秘密  -对  秘密
- Secret? - Yes, a secret.
今天中午12点
12:00 today,
门口的守卫将离开岗位
the guards at those doors will leave their posts
而换岗的守卫会迟到五分钟
and their replacements are going to be five minutes late.
迟到五分钟
Late five minutes.
没错  迟到五分钟  12点整
Yes. Late five minutes. At 12:00.
仅此一天  仅此一次
Just today. Just this once.
没人把守大门
No one is going to be watching those doors.
-也没人看着你  -美国不关闭了
- And no one will be watching you. - So, America not closed.
没错
No.
这五分钟  美国的大门为您敞开
America, for five minutes, is open.
日安  纳沃斯基先生
Have a nice life, Mr. Navorski.
联合航空公司  最后一次登机广播
United Airlines, final boarding call...
捉了再放  乔奇  很简单
Catch and release, Judge. It's simple.
比如你钓上一条小鱼
Sometimes you land a small fish.
不要管他  把他放回水里
You unhook him and place him back in the water.
给他自由
You set him free so that
让别人也体验一下捉他的感觉
somebody else can have the pleasure of catching him. All right.
好  开始吧
All right, here we go. Go, go, go.
叫他们走
Okay. Call them off.
约翰逊  从门边撤离
Johnson, clear the doors.
好的  走
All right. Go.
从那撤离  门口没人了
Get out of there. All right, there's the door.
好了  他上哪儿去了
Here we go. Now where is he?
-这里  -不  那不是他  -确定吗
- There he is. - No, that's not him. - Are you sure?
在这儿
There he is. Okay.
维克多  好样的
All right, Viktor. Here we go.
很复杂吗  出去啊  维克多
What's so complicated? Exit, Viktor.
等出去了  你就是别人的麻烦了
Come on. In a couple of minutes, you'll be somebody else's problem.
他不想让别人看见
He wants to make sure nobody's watching.
我跟他说了没人看着
No, I told him nobody would be watching.
快  没错  就是这样
Come on. All right, here we go.
-呼叫机场警察  -他们就来
- Call the Airport Police. - He's on his way.
不好意思
Excuse me.
就是这样  往前走
You got it. There we go.
我猜他是想跑过去  快离开
He's got to get a running start, I guess. Come on. Just leave.
离开  离开  离开
Just leave. Leave. Leave.
你干什么呢  为什么跪下  祈祷吗
What are you doing? What's he doing? Why is he kneeling? Is he praying?
不  他在系鞋带
No. He's tying his shoelace.
走啊  快移开摄像头
Come on, leave. Get the cameras.
他在哪儿  他在哪儿
Where is he? Where is he?
-在左边  -不  他刚才还在门边呢
- To the left of here. - No. He was just at the door.
-往左点  -好的
- Just go a little left. - All right.
我等着
I wait.
看什么看  都干嘛呢  回去工作
What are you looking at? What are you doing? Go back to work. Thank you.
该死的
Oh, God. Shit.
-这是你的吗  -谢谢
- This belong you? Please, please. - Thank you.
该死
Oh, shit.
看  地板湿滑
See? Wet floor.
这小人就是你
That you.
我要迟到了
I'm so late.
布宜诺斯艾利斯  我记不住登机口了
Buenos Aires. I just can't remember the gate.
24号登机口
Gate 24.
-你确定  -是的
- You sure? - Yes.
谢谢
Thanks.
等一下
Wait.
给你  倍耐斯鞋子
For you. Payless Shoes.
二楼  鞋跟结实
Second floor. Sensible heels.
-宝贝  -过来
- Hi, baby. - Come here, you.
我觉得他是中情局派来监视我们的
I think he's CIA. The CIA put him here to spy on us.
你说什么呢
You don't know what you're talking about.
他都不会说英语
He doesn't speak English.
这家伙要是不会
If he could not speak, this guy.
要是他不会说英语
He can't speak English,
他怎么可能搭讪上漂亮姑娘呢
how could he have a meeting with a beautiful woman?
和一个空姐
A flight attendant.
-她也是中情局的吗  -不是
- Oh, so, she's CIA, too? - No.
她像俄国人  克格勃
She look like a Russian. KGB.
她把自己的鞋跟给了他
She gave him heel of her shoes.
而他给了她一张纸
And he gave her a piece of the paper.
-微缩胶卷吗  -倍耐斯鞋店的优惠劵
- Was it microfilm? - A coupon from Payless Shoes.
肯定是某种暗号
Must be some kind of the code.
伙计  你清洁剂吸多了变神经了
Buddy, I think you've been spending too much time inhaling them cleaning products.
我提醒你们  都小心点
I'm warning you guys. You watch yourself.
这家伙待在这肯定有原因  为了我们
This guy is here for a reason. And I think that reason is us.
借过  伙计
Excuse me, buddy.
怎么了
What's going on?
是纳沃斯基  他学会赚硬币了
It's Navorski. He's figured out the quarters.
下午好  欢迎光临汉堡王  您要什么
Good afternoon. Welcome to Burger King. May I take your order?
不用找了
Keep the change.
借过
Excuse me.
走开  走开
Okay, go. Go.
真乖  真乖  谢谢  谢谢
Good boy. Good boy. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
再见
Bye-bye.
欢迎光临汉堡王  请问...
Burger King. May I take your...
危机  卡科吉亚
"Crisis. Krakozhia."
战争基本平息
Now that heavy fighting has subsided
双方都在积蓄力量以应对寒冬
and both sides have dug in for the long winter ahead,
显然 卡科吉亚未来的局势仍不明朗
it's clear that the future of Krakozhia may be in doubt for some time to come.
而卡科吉亚人民饱受内战之苦
Meanwhile, the people of Krakozhia suffer the consequences.
食物...
"And food..."
食物和能源短缺
Have caused food and energy shortages.
在卡科吉亚
"...In Krakozhia."
百老汇的故事...
"The story of Broadway is the..."
热门喜剧《老友记》的演员
"The cast" "Of comedy hit Friends,"
该剧设定在纽约
"Which is set in New York."
老友
Friends.
女士们先生们  由于天降大雪
Ladies and gentlmen, due to the heavy snowfall,
所有航班都将取消...
all flights have been canceled...
韦恩·牛顿今天六十一岁了
"Wayne Newton is 61 today."
真是个奇迹
"It's a miracle."
韩国连体婴儿今日在迈阿密分离
"Korean conjoined twins separated today in Miami."
生存几率百分之五十
"Chances of survival 50-50."
百分之五十
50-50.
下一个
Next.
我想问您  纳沃斯基先生
Let me ask you something, Mr. Navorski.
您明知道没法通过
Why do you wait here every
为什么还要在这排好久的队
day when there's nothing I can do for you?
美国不承认您的国家
Your new visa will not arrive
您是不会有签证的
until your country is recognized by the U.S.
你有两个章
You have two stamp.
一个红的  一个绿的
One red, one green.
-所以呢  -我有百分之五十的机会
- So? - I have chance to go New York, 50-50.
你这么想还真是乐观
Yes. That's a beautiful way to look at it,
可惜美国不是这样的
but America doesn't work that way.
作为机场外勤专员
As acting Field Commissioner,
我要为肯尼迪机场设立一个新岗位
I've created a new position here at JFK.
乘客交通联络员
Transportation Liaison for Passenger Assistance.
这个人做什么呢
Sir, what will that person do?
谢谢  交给我吧
Thank you. I'll take it from here.
我是乘客交通联络员
I'm Transportation Liaison in charge of Passenger Assistance.
没推车就没钱  没有钱就没吃的
No carts, no quarters. No quarters, no food.
要不了几天他就会迈过那道门
It'll be days before he goes through the doors
违反第2.14条条款
in violation of section 2.14.
然后他就是别人的麻烦了
Then he's somebody else's problem.
为什么我们不现在宣布他违法了条款
Sir, why don't we tag him in violation of section 2.14 now?
然后拘留他
Then ship him to detention.
他离开航站楼才算犯法
He has to break the law by leaving this terminal.
我绝不会为了摆脱这种人而撒谎的
I won't lie, particularly to get rid of somebody like Victor Navorski.
-抱歉伙计  -亲爱的
- Sorry, buddy. - Honey!
放下  放下
Put it down. Put it down.
放下
Put it down.
你抢了我的拖把  你抢了我的地盘
You try to take my mop. You try to take my floor.
这是我的工作
It's my job.
离我的地盘远点  离我的拖把远点
Stay off my floor. Stay away from my mop.
-吃的  -你要再碰我就杀了你
- Food. - If you touch it again, I kill you.
我叫恩里克·克鲁兹
Hey. I'm Enrique Cruz.
我想和你谈谈
We need to talk.
-我想和你做个交易  -什么交易
- I want to make a deal with you. - What deal?
我需要海关官员托蕾丝的信息
I need information on CBP Officer Torres.
你给我信息  我给你吃的
You feed me information about her, and I'll feed you.
-你想知道些什么  -你每天都见到她
- What do you want know? - You see her every day.
我想知道什么能让她腿软
I want to know what makes her knees weak.
什么能让她热血沸腾  欲火难耐
What makes her blood boil and her body tingle.
她是匹野马  你得帮我征服她
She's a wild stallion, and you'll help me break her.
我是...我是她的真命天子
I'm... I'm her man of mystery.
-托蕾丝官员是匹野马  -她的名字是多洛莉丝
- Officer Torres is wild stallion? - Her name is Dolores.
你帮我赢得她的芳心  我就让你吃饱
You help me to win her heart, and you'll never go hungry again.
-成交  -当真  你保证
- I do this. - Really? Promise?
-是的  -好的  谢谢你
- Yes. - Okay. Thank you.
野马什么意思
What mean, "Wild stallion"?
托蕾丝官员  我朋友说你是匹野马
Officer Torres. My friend say you are stallion.
纳沃斯基先生
Mr. Navorski.
-是什么  -野马  一种马
- A what? - Stallion, like a horse.
站到黄线后面去
Stand behind the yellow line.
-是一种很漂亮的马  -谁说的
- It's beautiful horse. - Who said that?
你喜欢吃的吗  我朋友运吃的
You like food? My friend drive the food.
纳沃斯基先生  站到黄线后面去
Mr. Navorski, behind the yellow line.
-轮到你时我再帮你  -我拿浅绿色表
- I will help once it's your turn. - I'll get light green.
-浅绿色表格  -我马上回来
- Light green form. Okay. - I'll be back.
她说了件事
She say one thing.
-很重要  -什么  她说什么
- Very important. - What? What did she tell you?
怎么了  三文鱼不好吃吗
You don't like it? Something wrong with the salmon?
-来点寂寞  -什么
- Need gorchitsa. - What?
芥末  芥末
Mustard. Mustard?
-芥末吗  -是的
- Mustard? - Yes. Please.
谢谢
Thank you.
托蕾丝官员  你喜欢电影吗
Officer Torres, you like the films?
-电影  -不怎么喜欢
- Movies? - Not so much.
-那舞蹈团演出呢  -看不起
- The Rockettes? - Can't afford it.
-你喜欢什么  -漫展
- What do you like? - Conventions.
漫展  那是什么
Conventions. What is?
-就是漫展  -漫展
- Conventions. - Conventions?
是什么私密的地方吗
This is like secret place you go?
她穿成兰德秘书的样子去漫展
She go to these conventions dressed as Yeoman Rand.
-兰德秘书  -她是星际迷航迷
- Yeoman Rand. - She's a Trekkie.
最喜欢的一集是《末日机器》
Favorite episode is "Doomsday Machine."
好了  维克多
Now, listen, Viktor.
你得问她点非常重要的事情
You gotta ask her something that is very important.
好的
Okay.
-我等着  -祝您旅途愉快
- I wait. - Enjoy your visit.
下一个
Next.
-托蕾丝官员  -纳沃斯基先生
- Officer Torres. - Mr. Navorski.
给你选择
You have choose.
有钱的男人还是爱你的男人
Man with money or man with love?
你选什么
What is choose?
她有过男朋友
She had a boyfriend?
谈了多久  两年
For how long? Two years?
出了什么事
What happened?
他屁退了
He chit.
-什么  -他屁退了
- What? - He chit.
什么屁
Eat shit?
屁退  屁退  屁退
He chit. He chit. He chit.
她原话怎么说的
Try to repeat exactly what she said.
他屁退了  被她抓到了  所以...
He chit. She catch him. So...
-他劈腿了  -对
- He cheats. - Yes.
我们管这个叫偷人  我们说偷人
What we call krushkach. We say krushkach.
一个男人  两个女人
One man, two womans.
就这样
So.
人太多了
Crowded, you know. Eh!
明白了  他劈腿了
Okay. He cheats.
-说劈腿  -屁退
- You say "Cheats." - He chit.
-不  是劈腿  -恩里克
- No, "Cheat." - Enrique.
你不许劈腿
You, no chit.
-绝不劈腿  -绝不屁退
- No cheat. - No chit.
我不会劈腿的  不是屁退
No. I won't cheat. Not shit.
她是个好女孩  她不会容忍你屁退的
She's a nice girl. She won't take your chitting.
下一个
Next.
托蕾丝官员  你爱过谁吗
Officer Torres. Have you been ever in the love?
够了  维克多  这人是谁
Enough, Viktor. Who is it?
谁让你跑来打听这些的
Who's telling you to ask me these things?
是个苦情郎
It's a man of misery.
苦情
Misery?
-是暗恋吗  -不  苦情  苦情郎
- Mystery? - No, no. Misery. Man of misery.
他太痛苦了  因为爱得太深
He's so sick. He's so in love.
但她说什么了
But what did she say?
她以前说"下一个下一个"
She did say, "Next, next."
现在却说"请  请过来"
And now she say, "Please. Please come."
这是...等一下
That's...wait.
-我马上到  -不  等等  维克多
- I coming now. - No, wait. Viktor.
维克多  再多透露点
Viktor, just tell me more.
我来了  我来了
I coming. I coming.
借过  借过
Please, please.
传呼机响了  嗡嗡叫
Beeper went off. Started beeping.
我抓起它  我来了
So, I grab. I come.
我们想出了一个办法
We have an idea.
要吃点东西吗  你好像饿了
Would you like something to eat? It looks like you're starving.
不  不用吃的  我饱了
No. No food. I stuffed.
谢谢
Thank you.
纳沃斯基先生  我有个好消息
So, Mr. Navorski, I have some very good news for you.
什么消息
What?
我想出了一个让你离开机场的办法
I've figured out a way to get you out of this airport.
怎么做
How?
我们有相关的法规
Well, we have laws here that protect aliens
可以保护害怕回到自己国家的人
who have a credible fear of returning to their own country.
如果我们能确定你也害怕
If we can establish this fear with you,
海关就会启动加速处理程序
then the CBP will be forced to begin Expedited Removal Procedures,
他们会把你送到移民法庭
to bring you to an immigration
并让你申请政治避难
judge and let you plead your case for asylum.
政治避难
Asylum.
不幸的是  法院有太多的政治避难诉求
Unfortunately, the courts are so backed up with asylum cases
最快的话也要六个月
that the soonest you'd get before a judge would be six months from now.
我们也别无选择
Yes, and we would have no choice
这六个月只能放你出去
but to let you go for those six months.
这是法律  先放你自由
It's the law. You'd be released.
你可以在纽约等待审理的那一天
You would be free to wait in New York until your court date.
但是信不信由你
But, believe it or not,
大部分人再也没出现过
most people never show up before the judge.
所以我去纽约了
So I go New York City?
你今晚就可以去纽约
You can go to New York City tonight.
不过我们必须先确定你确实害怕
But you only get to go if we can establish a credible fear.
-害怕  -害怕
- Fear? - Fear.
-害怕什么  -问得好
- From what? - That's the best part.
你害怕什么不重要
It doesn't matter what you're afraid of.
对美国政府来说都一样
It's all the same to Uncle Sam.
我会问你一个问题  很简单
So I'm going to ask you one question, a very simple question.
如果你答对了
If you give me the correct answer,
我今晚就能让你离开机场
I can get you out of this airport tonight.
所以我只需要回答一个问题
So, I answer one question.
今晚就能去纽约了
Go to New York City. Tonight.
-今晚  -今晚
- Tonight. - Tonight.
好的  好的
Okay. Okay.
好的
Okay.
请问此时此刻
Do you, at this time,
你是否害怕回到你的祖国
have any fear of returning to your own country?
不
No.
我再问你一次
Okay. Let me try it again.
-你的国家在打仗  -对  在打仗
- Your country's at war. - Yes. War.
街上有持枪暴徒  还有政治迫害
There are men in the streets with guns. Political persecution.
-是的  很可怕  -对  非常可怕
- Yes. It's terrible. - Yeah, it's horrible.
天知道会发生什么
And God only knows what could happen.
无辜的人们在睡梦中被抓走扔进监狱
Innocent people are torn from their beds and thrown into jail.
星期二  我恨星期二
On Tuesdays. I hate Tuesdays.
所以你害怕
So you're afraid.
-害怕什么  -卡科吉亚
- From what? - Krakozhia.
-你害怕卡科吉亚  -卡科吉亚
- You're afraid of Krakozhia. - Krakozhia?
不  我不怕卡科吉亚
No, I am not afraid from Krakozhia.
我倒是有点怕这间屋子
I'm a little afraid of this room.
街上有炸弹  人的尊严扫地
I'm talking about bombs. I'm talking about human dignity.
我们在谈人权
I'm talking about human rights.
维克多  不用担心  告诉我
Viktor, please don't be afraid to tell me
你害怕卡科吉亚
you're afraid of Krakozhia.
那是家  我不害怕我的家
Is home. I am not afraid from my home.
怎么样  我现在去纽约了吗
So? I go to New York City now?
-不行  -不行
- No. - No?
好吧
Okay.
-我怕鬼  -非常感谢
- I'm afraid from ghosts. - Thanks very much.
-我害怕德古拉  -非常感谢
- I'm afraid from Dracula. - Thanks a lot.
我害怕狼人  我害怕鲨鱼
I'm afraid from Wolfmens, afraid from sharks.
非常感谢
Thanks a lot.
-为什么要这样  -美国人不看标牌
- Why you do this? - Nobody read the sign in America.
这是我惟一的乐趣
This is the only fun I have.
烧烤派对  所以我不能见你了
A barbecue? That's why I'm not going to see you?
直说吧  我调了时间就为了见你
Let me get this straight. I change my schedule to meet you.
我连飞了四班
I take four back-to-back flights,
绕着世界飞了27个小时
fly 27 hours straight literally around the world,
可现在你却告诉我
and now you tell me you're
你要和你老婆一起过国庆节
going to spend July 4th with your wife?
她还不喜欢烟火
The woman hates fireworks.
别撒谎好吗
Don't lie to me, okay?
我知道你上周末带她去罗马了
I know for a fact you took her to Rome last weekend.
因为你坐的是美联航  麦克斯
Because you flew United, Max.
你爱偷听别人电话吗
You make a habit out of listening to other people's conversations?
不  我在给家里打电话
No, I try to call home.
所以...
So then...
-你知道为什么男人都是混蛋吗  -不
- You know why men are such assholes? - No.
暂时无法使用
因为他们都是骗子
Because they're all liars.
等等
Wait.
地板湿滑
Wet floor.
小心点  别受伤了
Please. Don't be hurt.
怎么可能不受伤  他结婚了
How can I not be? He's married.
一男两女  人太多了
One man. Two womens. Crowded.
你想知道最糟糕的是什么吗
You want to know what the worst part is?
我从没叫过他离开他的妻子
I never asked him to leave his wife.
我还鼓励他去调解
I encouraged him to get counseling.
我这人真有病
What kind of sick person am I?
我居然还为他们加油打气
I'm rooting for the home team.
可是跟他做爱实在太棒了
I just wish the sex wasn't so amazing.
-太棒了  -再见
- So amazing. - Bye-bye.
有时候  早上起来
You know, sometimes in the mornings,
我的目光越过客房服务落在他身上
I just stare at him over room service.
看他玩字谜游戏
Watch him do the crossword puzzle.
我不禁想  也许真的有可能
I start to think that maybe, maybe this could happen.
我们能相厮守
That we belong together.
这男的已经拥有你了
This man has you.
还迷惑[字谜]什么
Why he need puzzle?
都是我的错
This is my problem.
我总是一厢情愿地看男人
I always see men the way I want to see them.
我好像在什么地方见过你
Do I know you from someplace?
鞋跟结实  倍耐斯鞋子  二楼
Sensible heels. Payless Shoes. Second floor.
你要回家吗
You headed for home?
不  不  我
No, no. I am...
我的班机延误了很久
I am delayed a long time.
真讨厌飞机延误  你是做什么的
I hate it when they delay flights. What do you do?
我从一栋楼到另一栋楼
Oh, I go from one building to another building.
我有个传呼机
I have beeper.
承包商啊  你们也经常飞来飞去
Oh, contractors. You guys travel as much as we do.
失礼了  谢谢你
Sorry about that. Thank you very much.
BH是什么意思
What's "BH"?
用英文说
In English,
维克多·纳沃斯基
Viktor Navorski.
-用英文说  我叫阿米莉亚·沃伦  -阿米莉亚·沃伦
- In English, Amelia Warren. - Amelia Warren?
-很高兴认识你  -我也是
- Nice to meet you. - You, too.
很高兴再次见到你
Nice to see you again.
你喜欢意大利菜吗
You like Italian food?
时候不早了  你也许有别的安排
I know, it's late and you've probably got other plans,
不过如果你想一起吃个饭的话
but if you'd like to grab some dinner,
我们可以出去拦个的士
we can run right out and catch a cab.
我知道有个地方的烤碎肉卷很好吃
I know a place that has the greatest cannelloni.
不行
No, I can't.
-你结婚了吗  -没有
- You married? - No.
-有女朋友了吗  -没有
- Girlfriend? - No.
我不能和你出去
I can't go out with you.
天啊  对不起
God. I'm so sorry.
实在对不起
I am so sorry.
我是脑子短路了还是怎么的
I must come off like a complete nut job or something.
-不是的  -我只是不想一个人吃饭
- No. - I just, I didn't want to eat alone.
你能理解吗
You ever done that before?
地板湿滑
Wet floor.
-不  我  -不  你不需要解释
- No, I... - Oh, please, You don't have to explain. It's fine.
娜迪亚
Nadia.
在纽约的餐馆里
In New York restaurant,
烤碎肉卷多少钱
what cost is cantaloni?
我不清楚  15块吧
I don't know. Maybe 15 bucks.
-美元吗  -20块
- Dollars? - Twenty.
两个人40块
Two people, 40.
Two people, 40 dollars.
两个人40块
我帮你吗
I help you?
先生  对不起  已经招到人了
I'm so sorry, sir. The position has already been filled.
-你住在附近吗  -67号登机口
- Do you live nearby? - Yes. Gate 67.
我们需要非常准时
Because we are very particular about punctual...
你刚说67号登机口吗
Did you say Gate 67?
67号登机口
Gate 67.
你是在开玩笑吧
You got to be kidding.
你得帮我个忙啊
You got to help me help you.
社保号  驾照号全都没有
I don't see a Social Security number, driving license number,
地址  连电话号码都没有
mailing address, even a phone number.
你要电话号码吗  我有电话
Telephone? You need? I get. I get. I get phone.
我有电话
I get phone.
4511226
451-1226.
好了  什么时候打给你合适
All right. And when's the best time to reach you?
现在可以吗
Now?
-你好  -你好  纳沃斯基
- Hello? - Hi, Mr. Navorski.
我是维克多·纳沃斯基  你是谁
Yes, this is Viktor Navorski. Who calls?
我是新发现的克里夫
It's Cliff from the Discovery Store.
克里夫  你好
Ah! Cliff. Hello.
-还好吗  -很好
- How's it going? - Good.
-现在方便接电话吗  -正等你来电呢
- Is this a good time? - Yes, I wait for your call all day.
我要告诉你  我们招到人了
Well, I got to tell you that the position's been filled.
你可以到别的地方坐吗
Yeah, so could you please go sit someplace else?
-我去个洗手间  -很好
- I go to bathroom now. - That'd be good.
-好的  -谢谢
- All right. - Thank you.
好的
Okay.
这是谁
Who is this?
-你是谁  -不知道
- Who are you? - It's no one.
这里两周没人来过了  他不是我的人
There's no one here for two weeks. This isn't one of my guys.
看这挑檐做得真好
Look at this cornicing. This is good work.
一定是哈利的人  你是哈利的人吗
Must be Harry's crew. You with Harry's crew?
哈利以为这是他负责的吗
Does Harry think he's running this job?
-我这就走  -走去哪里
- I go now. - Go where?
-67号登机口  -67号
- Gate 67. - 67?
还有十个月67号才开工呢
We're ten months away from 67.
如果他不是我们的人  一定是哈利的
He's got to be Harry's. If he's not mine, and he's not yours...
哈利是存心让我难堪
Harry's trying to make me look bad.
在他没抢到67号前  我要拖慢他
I've got to slow him down before he gets to 67.
-你叫什么名字  -维克多·纳沃斯基
- What's your name? - Viktor Navorski.
把他从哈利那给我挖来
Pull him off Harry's crew, put him on mine.
周一早上六点半来上班
You start 6:30 Monday morning.
你要雇用我吗
You give me job?
好的  老大  六点半
6:30, yes, boss.
今天午夜  不要迟到
我们有意大利航空公司的龙虾馄饨
We have lobster ravioli from Alitalia.
俄罗斯航空公司的鱼子酱
We have caviar from Russian Aeroflot.
好的  上菜吧
Okay. Just bring it.
-维克多  -大家好
- Hey, Viktor. - Hello, all.
瞧  没有国家的人
Look. The man without a country.
过来吧  欢迎
Come on in. Welcome.
-我看到了这个  -干得好
- I see this. - You did well.
请坐
Have a seat.
-这吗  -是的
- Here? - Here.
快来  坐下
Come on, sit down.
-谁邀请他的  -我请的  三缺一啊
- Who invited him? - I did. We needed a fourth, right?
-我不要跟他玩  -古普塔  别这样
- I'm not going to play with him. - Oh, Gupta, relax, would you?
-他不是间谍  -你怎么知道
- He isn't a spy. - How do you know?
他可能会录下我们的谈话
He could be recording everything we say.
他的衣服里有窃听器
A wire in his shirt.
屁眼里有麦克风
A microphone up in his ass.
-我不想丢了饭碗  -好吧
- I'm not going to lose my job. - Fine.
-要不我们给他照个X光  -好
- Would you feel better if we x-rayed him? - Yes.
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes.
-好啦  你没问题  -那就玩牌去
- Okay. So you are clean. - Good. Let's play cards.
我星期五才有钱
I will have money. But Friday.
别担心
Don't worry about it.
我们赌的是失物招领处的东西
We play for unclaimed items from the Lost and Found.
来吧  看看都有什么稀奇古怪的东西
You'll be amazed at what people leave at airports. Come.
我有两个9  再加两个9
I have two nines and two nines.
四个9  你是我的了
Four nines. Take you.
-小心点  -当心
- Careful, careful. - Watch out.
等等
Wait.
我们有个问题想问你  维克多
We have a question for you, Viktor.
我们只是出于好奇
Yeah, we're just curious.
罐子里装的是什么
What is in the can?
-啥  这个吗  -照X光时发现的
- What? This? - Yeah, we saw the x-ray.
里面不是坚果
We know there's no nuts in there.
里面有什么
What is in there?
爵士
This is jazz.
-爵士  -是的  爵士
- Jazz? - Jazz, yes.
-爵士  -是的
- Jazz? - Yes.
你确定是爵士吗  有可能是蓝调哦
You sure it's jazz in there? It might be the blues.
-或是萨尔萨舞曲  -可能是斯蒂维·旺德[歌手]
- Or salsa. - Yeah, maybe it's Stevie Wonder.
-不  是爵士  -好了  大伙
- No, no, is jazz. - Okay, guys. Okay.
今晚的大奖是
For tonight's grand prize, we have...
拿出来  古普塔
Show them, Gupta.
我在楼上发现了这个
I found this upstairs.
维珍航空头等舱的休息室里
Virgin Air, first class lounge.
谁的
And they belong to?
-夏尔  -夏尔的吗
- Cher. - Cher?
-是那个夏尔  -是的
- As in Cher? - Yeah. Cher.
我检查过了  还有目击证人
I checked it out. There were witnesses.
这就是夏尔的内裤
Those are Cher's panties.
-准备好了吗  -快
- Ready? - Hurry up.
我们要分享这内裤吗
So, will we share the panties?
-不行  -我赢了可不分享
- No, no, no. - Not if I win.
-快点  -等等
- Come on. - Wait a second.
飞往成田机场的801号航班
Flight number 801 to Narita
准备要起飞了
is now announcing final boarding...
不行  这是我的
"You can't. That is mine."
真是看不透你
"You can get so confused."
维克多  你好啊
Viktor? Well, hi.
我来  我来
Please.
-你好吗  -很好
- How are you? - Good.
上次的事真是抱歉
I gotta say, I am so sorry about what happened last time.
那样约你太唐突了
You knew, asking you out like that.
飞机上的人总想着摸我屁股
I'm so used to guys trying to grab my ass at 30,000 feet
突然遇到个中规中矩的人
that when I finally meet somebody keep his hands in his pocket,
我却不知道怎么办了
I don't know how to react.
-我们重新认识吧  -好
- Let's just start over. - Yes, okay.
-你是要走还是刚到  -两者都是吧
- Are you coming or going? - I don't know. Both.
-是吗  -拿破仑吗
- Tell me about it. - Napoleon?
我喜欢有关历史的书
Yeah. I read a lot of history books.
页数多  价格低  故事都是打打杀杀
They're long and cheap and usually about men killing each other.
1200页十美元不到  怎么不心动
Like 1,200 pages for $9.99. You can't beat that.
-拿破仑啊  -是的  我很喜欢他
- But Napoleon? - Yeah. He's one of my favorites.
-你知道什么救了拿破仑一命吗  -不
- You know what saved Napoleon's life? - No.
-他的自负  -自负
- His ego. - Ego?
在他经历滑铁卢的惨败之后
After he loses the Battle of Waterloo,
拿破仑把自己禁闭在圣赫勒拿岛
Napoleon isolates himself on the tiny island of Saint Helena.
接下来发生什么  没人知道
No one knows exactly what happens next.
但我喜欢的版本是这样的
But the version I like goes like this.
他意志消沉  决定结束自己的生命
He's very depressed and decides to take his own life.
拿破仑相信自己天赋秉异
But Napoleon believes himself to be of such superhuman strength
所以  他服用了比常人多六倍的毒药
that he takes six times the amount of poison needed to do the job.
把他的胃撑坏了  结果吐了
His stomach is so full up with poison that his body rejects it,
所以没死
and he doesn't die.
瞧  自负救了他一命
See? Ego. Saved his life.
也许他需要一副眼镜
Maybe he need glasses.
-眼镜  -用来读瓶子上的字
- Glasses? - Yes. To read words on bottle.
是毒药
Poison.
你说得还真有点道理
You know it's funny you should say that.
传言拿破仑是个远视眼
Rumor has it that Napoleon was farsighted.
-就这样了  -就这样了
- There you go. - There you go.
-那就这样  -那就这样
- There you go. - And there you go.
维克多  我们是在改写历史哎
Viktor, I think we're rewriting history right here.
要不边吃午饭边聊吧
Why don't we talk about it over lunch?
真不敢相信  我居然又约你了
I can't believe it. I just asked you out again.
我居然又干这事了
I just did it again.
我  离我远点  维克多
I'm so... Just stay away from me, Viktor, okay?
我有病  我受不了身边没人
I'm sick. I don't have the ability to be alone for five seconds.
可以
Okay.
-可以什么  -可以
- Okay, what? - Okay.
和你吃午饭
Lunch with you.
-你要跟我吃午饭吗  -是的
- You'll have lunch with me? - Yes.
你不用赶飞机或者
You're not running for a flight or...
我在等
I wait.
-我的  -是你的
- It's me. - You. Yes.
对不起  我突然有事
I'm sorry. I just got paged.
-工作么  -不是
- You work? - No.
三个人  太多了
Three of you. Crowded.
离我远点  维克多
Stay away from me, Viktor.
我真的很有问题  我跟拿破仑一样坏
I'm... I have a serious problem. I'm as bad as Napoleon.
我一直跟坏男人交往
I just keep ingesting
直到我让自己恶心
these poisonous men until I make myself sick.
你没有问题  阿米莉亚
You're not sick, Amelia. No.
你只是远视
No. You're farsighted.
-我得走了  -我得留下
- I have to go. - I have to stay.
-这就是我的人生  -我也是
- Story of my life. - Oh! Me, too.
海关检阅在三天后
Your CBP inspection's in three days.
联邦调查局和国土安全局的人会巡视机场
The FBI and Homeland Security will tour the airport,
他们先花两个小时巡查办公室
spend two hours observing these
然后再跟你谈话
offices before your interview process begins.
纳沃斯基挣了多少钱
How much does Navorski make?
什么
Sir?
他挣了多少  他们给他多少
How much does he make? How much are they paying him?
他们应该是私下给他现金
I believe they're paying him cash under the table, sir.
我知道  那是多少
I know that. How much?
19美元一小时
$19 an hour.
难以置信  比我挣得还多
Unbelievable. Do you know that's more than I make?
纽约市建筑公司都这样
That's New York City construction.
有一天  我的一个手下来找我
One of my own men came up to me the other day.
问我要不要下注
Asked me if I wanted to join the big pool.
看看他
Look at him.
赌纳沃斯基什么时候离开机场
Place a bet on when Navorski's going to leave this airport.
你听说了吗
Have you heard about this?
我赌一月三号
I have January 3rd.
叫他过来
Bring him in.
杰克  他没有国籍  没有祖国
Jake, he has no nationality. Okay? No country.
从第二章第十二节章程看来
So, automatically, he's a national security risk,
他就是个安全隐患
according to my interpretation of section 2.12.
我只希望你把他拘留起来
So, all I asking for it's that you put him in
对他进行审查
a federal detention center and run a clearance on him.
就这个
That's all I want.
联邦监狱还有空位吗
Well, what about a federal prison?
别的机场呢
Well, what about another airport?
喂  喂
Hello? Hello?
咱这的人太多了  根本没有空间
I am just detaining so many people, there's no room anywhere.
联邦调查局呢
Did you try the FBI?
我谁都问了  没人收留他
Yes, I tried the FBI, I tried everybody. Nobody'll take him.
你要我带他回候机楼吗
You want me to bring him back to the terminal?
不  从现在开始  纳沃斯基住在这里
No. From now on, Navorski lives here.
今天要来的那些人
The people who are coming here today
是来监察我  审查我的
will be observing me, inspecting me.
但最主要的
But most of all they will
还是看这机场如何运作的
be looking at the way that this airport is run.
我们要让他们知道
So let's show them why this is
为什么这是美国最好的机场
the number one airport in the United States.
我们每天要接待600趟航班
We process about 600 planes a day,
平均每37分钟一班
with a processing time of 37 minutes per plane,
每60秒
about 60 seconds per passenger...
就有一位乘客入境
to be brought into the country.
工作量不小  所以我们得非常仔细
It's sort of a cruel stuff, so we keep it as clean as possible.
-你带什么入境  -电脑软件
- What do you import? - Computer software.
好大一堆核桃
That's a lot of walnuts.
我岳母很爱吃
Yeah. My mother-in-law loves these things.
我每次去巴西都会给她买一袋
Every time I go to Brazil, I bring her back a bag.
-你岳母  -是的
- Your mother-in-law? - Yeah.
我可以吃一个吗
Mind if I try one?
你怎么知道那不是给他岳母的
How did you know those weren't for his mother-in-law?
他要是有老婆  那戒指呢
If he's married, where's his wedding ring?
要是离了婚  谁还鸟岳母啊
And if he's divorced, who in their right mind still talks to their mother-in-law?
抱歉  没有冒犯岳母的意思
I'm sorry, but really. No offense to mother-in-laws, but...
-长官  -什么事
- Sir. - Yeah.
长官  楼上有紧急情况
Sir, we have a situation upstairs.
-那得等等  -等不了
- Oh, It's gonna have to wait. - No. This won't wait.
9点12分多伦多的一班飞机着陆后
When the 9:12 from Toronto landed,
他们查出了四瓶没有许可证的处方药
they found four prescriptions without an MPL.
他们想把药拿走  他就发疯了
They tried to take the pills away, and he went nuts.
他在那  我们认为药是给他爸爸的
There he is. We think they're for his father.
先生  冷静点  把武器放下
Sir, sir, calm down. Put your weapons down.
各位把武器收好  我们是来帮你的
Everybody keep your weapons... All right. We're here to help you.
我们是来帮你的  先生  把刀给我
We're here to help you, sir. All right. Give me the knife.
-他是哪里人  -俄罗斯
- Where's he from? - Russia.
唯一一个翻译官在纽瓦克  一个小时到
The only interpreter we got is in Newark. He'll be here in an hour.
-要找个人跟他沟通下  -我有个办法
- We have to get someone to talk to him. - I have an idea, sir.
维克多
Viktor.
我需要你的帮助
I need your help.
他叫米洛德拉戈维奇  就住在你的邻国
His name is Milodragovich. He lives across a board from you.
他可能听不懂你的方言
He may not speak exactly your dialect, whatever,
但我需要你翻译  帮我一把
but I need you to translate and help me out of the jam.
我帮你  为什么
I help you? Why?
因为我不希望有人受伤
Because I don't want anybody to get hurt.
这个人情绪很不稳定
This guy's very upset.
你跟他说说话  安抚一下他
Just talk to him and calm him down, right.
然后就能回航站楼了
Do that, and I'll let you back in the terminal.
不  纽约  不要红戳  要绿的
No. New York. No red stamp. Green. I green.
-纽约  -好吧
- New York. - Okay, yes.
-你说好  -好
- You say yes? - Yes.
-好  -好
- Yes. - Yes.
让开  让开
Stay out. Stay out.
米洛德拉戈维奇先生  他是来跟你谈谈的
Mr. Milodragovich. We have somebody here to talk to you.
跟你谈的  去吧
Somebody to talk to you. Go ahead.
让开  让开
Stay out. Stay out.
说什么
So?
告诉他  想要从这个国家出口药物
Okay, tell him in order to export medicines from this country,
就必须有相关文件
he needs to have the proper form,
必须要有相应的处方
he needs to have a Medicinal Purchase License.
你懂了吗  维克多
Okay? You understand me, Viktor?
他说这药是给他父亲的
He say he bring the medicine for his father.
这是他去加拿大的原因  给父亲药
This why he go to Canada. Medicine for father.
那都不重要
It doesn't matter.
他人在美国  就得按美国的规定来
His plane landed in the U.S. He needs to have the right form.
他不知道需要这些文件
He did not know he need this document.
没有人跟他说需要文件
No one say to him he need document form.
我告诉他了
I'm saying it to him.
他必须持有
He needs to have the form
他父亲所在的医院
signed by the local hospital who is treating his father
和加拿大医生签名的文件
and a doctor in Canada.
这些药必须留在美国
These medicines have to stay in the United States.
既然带来了  它们必须留在美国
Now that they are here. They have to stay here.
-他在求你  -我知道  我能看出来
- He's begging you. - I know. I can see that he's begging.
对不起  先生
I'm sorry, sir.
你需要乘坐早上的航班
You'll have to take a flight in the morning.
这些药必须留在这里
The medicine stays here.
不好意思
I'm sorry.
按住他
Send him down.
谢谢  维克多  做得不错  走吧
Thank you, Viktor. Good job. Let's go.
山羊
Goat.
-什么  -山羊  药是给山羊用的
- What? - Goat. Medicine is for goat.
-山羊  -对  药是给山羊用的
- Goat? - Yes. Medicine is for goat. Goat.
-他说的吗  -对
- He said that? - Yes.
他说
He say...
我误会了  我没理解"山羊"
We not understand. I not understand "Goat."
你说什么  你没理解他的意思
Why? What are you saying? You misunderstood him?
-这不是为了救他父亲的命  -不
- It's not for his dying father? - No. No.
卡科吉亚语里"父亲"
The... Krakozhia... the name for "Father"
听起来像"山羊"
sound like "Goat."
我听错了
I make mistake.
你为什么要这么做  维克多
Why are you doing this, Viktor?
药是给山羊的
Medicine is for goat.
-不  不是  -是的
- No, it's not. - Yes.
你看了那个蓝色的移民申请表
You read the blue immigration form.
-蓝色  -对  蓝色
- Blue? - Yes. Blue.
- Blue? - Blue. The blue form.
上面写着如果是动物用药
The one that says if it's an animal,
他就不需要许可
he doesn't need the medicinal purchase license.
你知道这一点  这样他就能把药带走
You know it. Then he can bring the drugs in.
不错  维克多  很不错
That's good, Viktor. That's very good.
你为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this? Huh?
你们素昧平生  你不懂法律
You don't know him. You don't know the rules.
看着我
Look at me.
我是想帮你
I was going to help you.
我要你问他  不  不是你
Now I want you to ask him... No, not you.
我要你问他  我要听他说
I want you to ask him. I want to hear him say it.
我要听他说药是给谁用的
I want to hear him say who the medicine is for.
拜托  药是给谁用的
Please. Who the medicine is for.
回答他  米洛德拉戈维奇先生  药是给谁的
Answer him, Mr. Milodragovich. Who are the pills for?
好了  药留下  他走  事情结束
Okay. The pills stay. He goes. That's it.
山羊
Goat.
药是给山羊的
Medicine for goat.
把药给他
Give him the pills.
药是给山羊的
Medicine for goat.
药是
Medicine...
他很爱那头羊
He love that goat.
你觉得这是个游戏吗
Do you think it is a game?
你以为我没理由把你扔进监狱
Do you think I need an excuse to put you back in that cell
关你五年吗
to keep you there for five years?
你向我宣战
You go to war with me,
就是向美国宣战
and you go to war with the United States, the America.
那样你就会见识到为什么战争结束后
Then you'll know why when the fight is over
卡科吉亚人买草纸都要排队
Krakozhians wait in line for cheap toilet paper
而山姆大叔都用双层查敏擦屁股
while Uncle Sam wipes his ass with Charmin two-ply.
当时有个二十岁的男人
There was a 20 man.
移民局的人已经拔出了枪
Immigration gun was drawn.
迪克逊已经准备开枪
The Dixon was ready to fire.
杀掉那个带着药的男人
To kill the little man with the pills.
但是有个人走进房间
But then someone walks into
站在那个男人的面前说道
the room and stand in front of this little man.
他说  "把枪拿开"
"Put the guns away," The man say.
"今天不会有人死去"
"Nobody will die today."
谁
Who?
-是谁救了他  -对  告诉我们是谁
- Who was it that saved him? - Yeah, tell us. Who was it?
那个人到底是谁
Who was this man?
纳沃斯基  维克多·"山羊"·纳沃斯基
Navorski. Viktor "The Goat" Navorski.
情况不太妙  弗兰克
It doesn't look good, Frank.
我只是照章办事
I was just following the rules.
有时候就要无视条条框框
Sometimes you have to ignore the rules
跳出来  人才是最重要的
know where the bumpers and concentrate on the people.
人文关怀  我知道
The people, I know.
人文关怀  同情心  弗兰克
The people, compassion. Frank.
那是构成这个国家的基石
That's the foundation of this country.
你可以从纳沃斯基身上学到些东西
You could learn something from Navorski.
打起精神  还有机会呢
Cheer up. It's not over yet.
-这是给我的吗  -是的  是的
- Is that for me? - Yes. Yes.
这是维京岛的旗鱼
Is Virgin Isle sailfish.
给你的
For you.
挂墙上的
For wall.
挂墙上的鱼
Fish for wall.
你为什么想去纽约
Why do you want to go to New York City?
花生罐里装的又是什么
And what's in the can of peanuts?
承诺
Promise.
-罐子里装着一个承诺  -对  承诺
- A promise in the can? - Yes. A promise.
让我给你一个承诺  维克多
Let me make you a promise, Viktor.
一个被困在这里的人给你的承诺
And this is a promise that comes from a man who is stuck here.
一个也许还会被困在这里十年的人
A man who may be stuck here for the next ten years.
从现在开始  你和我将是排档
From now on, you and I are partners.
我在这  你就不能走
If I stay, you stay.
你绝对不可能踏入纽约市
You will not set one foot in New York City.
连一个脚趾都不能进入美国
Not a single toe in the United States of America.
你听懂了吗
Do you understand what I am saying to you?
是的
Yes.
你不喜欢鱼
You don't like fish.
你有没有过自己就住在机场里的感觉
Do you ever feel like you're just living in an airport?
我们不需要这么做  维克多
You know we don't have to do this, Viktor.
我可以用箱子把你运出去
I can ship you out in a crate.
我可以把你寄到美国的任何一个地方去
I can literrally mail you anywhere in the U.S.
我的食品车怎么样
What about my food cart?
他可以藏在里面  直接开出去
He can hide inside, and we'll drive right out the front door.
不行  我不能那样做
No. I can't do this.
你说需要我们帮忙的
I thought you said that you wanted us to help you.
-是的  -她叫什么
- I do. - What's her name?
阿米莉亚·沃伦
Amelia Warren.
咱不是想出去吗  怎么越走越深了
I thought we were looking for a way out, not a way in.
你最好小心点
You'd be better careful.
那些空姐和普通女人可不一样
Those flight attendants ain't like regular women, Viktor.
在不同的时区飞来飞去
Flying back and forth between all those time zones
她们的生物钟全乱套了
kind of messes with their biological clock or something.
她们随时准备着上床
They're always ready for sex.
不然你以为他们为什么一直笑
When do you think they can't stop smiling?
我找到了些东西
Okay, I found something.
我得走了  他们会来抓我们的
I am leaving. They will come for us.
古普塔  放松  你就看着门就行了
Gupta, will you relax? Just go out there and watch the door.
你会进监狱的  我才不要
You go in jail. Not me.
算了吧
For... You know what? Forget it.
-继续找  -沃伦  对吗
- Keep looking. - Warren, you said, right?
-没错  -沃伦
- Yes. Yes. - Warren.
阿米莉亚·简·沃伦
Amelia Jane Warren?
-简  -对
- Jane? - Yeah.
干得好  维克多  一级棒
Way to go, Viktor. First class.
-她什么时候回来  -三个星期后
- When she come back? - Three weeks.
阿米莉亚  想一起吃点什么吗
Amelia, would you like to get eat to bite?
吃点什么  碎肉卷
Bite to eat? Cantaloni?
吃点什么
Bite to eat?
什么吃点  什么吃点
Eat to bite? Eat to bite.
吃点什么  吃点什么  吃点什么
Bite to eat. Bite to eat. Bite to eat.
古普塔  你结过婚吗
Gupta, you been ever married?
-你说什么  -你结过婚吗
- What did you say? - You been ever married?
我在印度有老婆和两个小孩
I had a wife and two kids in India.
我二十三年前离开他们
I left them there 23 years ago.
为什么
Why?
我在马德拉斯开了个小香烟店
I had a small tobacco shop in Madras.
赚的钱刚够我活下去
Made just enough money to survive.
有天一个警察来  说我欠税
One day this policeman comes in and tells me I owe him some tax.
好吧  这很正常  所以我给了他
I said okay. This is common. So I pay him.
第二天  他又来了
The next day, the same policeman come
每天都来  每天都来
and keep coming and keep coming.
我不停地给他钱
And I am paying, and I'm paying him,
一直给  一直给
and I'm paying him, and I'm paying him.
直到第五天
And finally, on the fifth day,
我拿了把刀  一刀捅进他的胸口
I take a knife and I stab him in his chest.
-你杀了个警察  -不  我没扎中心脏
- You killed policeman? - No. I just missed his heart.
他们想抓我的时候  我跑了
When they tried to arrest me, I run away.
你从来没回过家
So you never go home?
如果我回去  会被判七年
If I go home, I go in the jail for seven years.
如果美国抓住你  遣送你回去怎么办
What if United States catch you? They deport you.
只要我好好搞卫生  低调点
As long as I keep my floor clean, keep my head down,
他们就不会遣送我
they have no reason to deport me.
他们不会注意到像我这样的人
They have no reason to notice a man like me.
来自意大利罗马的美国航空2703航班
United Airlines Flight 2703 from Rome, Italy,
现在抵达登机口C43
is now arriving at Gate C43.
-停一下  -我很抱歉
- Hey, wait. - Sorry. I'm sorry.
不  不   地很湿
No, no, no. It's wet.
-喂  -小心看路
- Hey. - Watch where you're going.
小心点
Watch out.
-阿米莉亚  -维克多
- Amelia. - Viktor.
-你好  -不好意思
- Hello. - Sorry. I'm sorry.
他差一点撞死我
He nearly killed me.
-你没事吧  -我没事
- You okay? - I'm fine.
我喜欢你的西装
I love the suit.
雨果·波士
Hugo Boss.
特价不到一百五
On sale, $149.99.
真不错
That's a bargain.
-拿破仑  -是的
- Napoleon? - Yes, yes.
还有约瑟芬
And Josephine.
你知道拿破仑在婚礼上给了约瑟芬什么吗
Do you know what Napoleon gave Josephine on their wedding day?
阿米莉亚
Amelia?
你想要吃点什么吗
Would you like to have eat to bite?
食物  今晚
Food. Tonight?
-你请我吃晚饭吗  -没错
- You're asking me out for dinner? - Yes.
当然
Yeah. Sure.
-什么时候  -晚餐的时候
- What time? - Dinnertime.
-你想去哪里  -我知道地方
- Where do you want to go? - I know place.
-你有预约吗  -纳沃斯基
- Do you have an appointment? - Navorski.
请跟我来
This way, please.
谢谢
Thank you.
这里居然有露台
I didn't know they had a patio up here.
这地方真不错
It's very nice.
晚上好
Good night.
小心  小心
Please. Please.
不好意思  今晚有意大利肉卷和鸡肉
Sorry. So, tonight we have cannellonis or chicken.
-请给我意大利肉卷  -意大利肉卷
- Cannelloni, please. - Cannelloni.
-不好意思  -谢谢
- Sorry. - Thank you.
您呢  先生
For you, sir?
-一样  -很棒的选择
- Same. - That's a great, great choice.
马上回来
I'll be back.
让我看一下  请用
Let me see. Enjoy.
你知道羊角面包是在罗马尼亚发明的吗
Did you know the croissant was invented in Romania?
-说说看  -好的
- Tell me. - Okay.
1742年  土耳其人入侵布加勒斯特
It's 1742, and the Turks invade Bucharest,
打算趁着夜幕奇袭
making a surprise attack under the cover of night.
可是小镇的面包师
But the town bakers...
不好意思
Sorry.
面包师怎么了
So, the bakers?
-没什么  一个无聊的故事  -说嘛
- No, never mind. It's a dumb story. - No, please.
对不起  维克多
I'm sorry, Viktor.
没人会在乎羊角面包在哪里发明
Nobody really cares where the croissant was invented.
我打赌罗马尼亚人自己也不在乎
I'll bet the Romanians themselves don't give a shit.
我在乎
I care.
这是历史  是真相
Is histories. Is truth.
-我三十九岁了  -不可能
- I'm 39 years old. - No.
-是真的  -不可能
- Yeah. - No.
-这是真相  -完全看不出来
- That's the truth. - You are not.
我告诉别人我三十三岁
I tell everybody I'm 33,
我大多数的约会对象觉得我二十七岁
and most of the men I've dated think I'm 27, but no.
我三十九了
I'm 39.
所以呢  我也曾经三十九岁过
So? I was 39 once.
我十八岁开始做空姐
I was 18 years old when I started working for the airlines.
我已经做了二十年了
I've been doing this over 20 years.
我装不下去了
And now there's no more pretending.
就这样
This is it.
我的通讯录按城市分类
It's why my address book is by city,
吃晚饭的时候呼机总是会响
and my pager will always go off during dinner.
你可以关掉呼机
You can switch off pager.
我也希望
I wish I could.
我等一个电话已经等了七年了
I've been waiting for a phone call for seven years.
我知道会来  维克多  所以不敢关机
I know it's coming, Viktor. That's why I can't break it off.
所以我不住旅馆
That's why I live out of hotels
带着行李箱时刻准备出发
and have my little suitcase packed, ready to go,
一旦他周末想见我
just in case he wants to meet me for the weekend.
我等了一辈子
I've been waiting my whole life.
就是不知道为什么要等
Just don't know what the hell for.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
我住在这里
I live here.
-什么  -我住在这里  就在候机楼
- What? - I live here, in terminal.
67号登机口
Gate 67.
-你住在机场里  -是的
- You live at the airport? - Yes. Day and night.
这是家  跟你一样  他们让我等
This home, like you. They tell me to wait.
所以我就等
So I wait.
经常坐飞机的都这么觉得  维克多
All frequent fliers feel the same way you do, Viktor.
所有人都在等  所有人
Everybody's waiting. Everybody.
等航班  等开会
For a flight, for a meeting...
我不等航班或者开会
I don't wait for flight or meeting.
那你等什么呢
Then what are you waiting for?
没关系  我懂的
Is okay. I understand.
我有个想法
I have an idea.
-过来  -你做什么
- Come here. - What you do?
-你确定吗  -不能更确定了
- You sure? - More than anything, I'm sure of this.
真的吗
Ready?
那你什么时候回来
So, when do you come back?
十三天以后  你呢
13 days. How about you?
我会在这里
I will be here.
万一你的行程变了呢
But what if your schedule changes?
我们是不是应该交换号码
Maybe we should exchange phone numbers.
不  我会在这里
No. I will be here.
你知道拿破仑打败巴伐利亚后给了约瑟芬什么吗
You know what Napoleon give to Josephine when he win Bavaria?
告诉我
Tell me.
拜托  告诉我吧
Come on. Tell me.
我会让你看到  十三天以后
I will show you. 13 days from now.
他在做什么
What's he doing?
我不能问他  我本应该知道他在做什么
I can't ask him. I'm supposed to tell him what he's doing.
如果我去问  会显得自己像个傻瓜
If I ask him, I look like an idiot.
不好意思  你必须帮我做这个
I'm sorry. Sorry. You got to do this for me.
我会给你很多很多好吃的
You'll get really fat with all the food I'm going to give you.
可是  拜托了  帮帮我
But, please, do this for me.
这是我拜托你做的最后一件事
It will be the last thing I ask you to do.
他在萨巴罗等你的答案
He waits for you to answer at Sbarro.
-我得工作  -他会等你
- I have to work. - He will wait.
礼拜堂
休 息 室
新婚燕尔
-旅途愉快吗  -不错
- How was your flight? - Good.
谢谢
Thanks.
-有什么事吗  -跟我们来一趟
- Is something wrong? - You'll have to come with us.
看玩笑吧  我每个月会来两次
You're kidding. I come through here twice a month.
请跟我来
Please follow me.
我跟朋友约好了见面
I'm supposed to be meeting somebody.
在我的世界里  只有三样事情重要
In my line of work, there are three things that matter.
人  文件  还有故事
The person, the document and the story.
弄明白其中一样  就全明白了
Find the truth of one, and you find the truth of all three.
我需要你帮我找出真相
I need your help finding the truth.
你认识一个叫维克多·纳沃斯基的人吗
Do you know a man named Viktor Navorski?
认识
Yes.
你知道他为什么来  从哪儿来吗
Do you know why he's here and where he's from?
不  我们只是朋友
No. We're just friends.
你有没有注意到
Have you noticed that he hides
他的行李中藏了一个烤花生罐头
a can of plenteous dry roasted peanuts in his bag?
-怎么了  -你觉得那是什么
- So? - What do you make of that?
我想可能是花生酱吧
I'd make peanut butter, I guess.
我们了解到他要去
We know that he's planning
莱克星顿的华美达酒店
to go to the Ramada Inn on Lexington.
-他告诉过你他来纽约的原因吗  -没
- Has he told you why he's in New York? - No.
他说过他住哪儿吗
Has he told you where he lives?
没有  我们只是在机场遇见
No. We just met at the airport.
我只知道他是建筑承包商
All I know is that he's a building contractor,
天天奔波
living out of a suitcase.
就这样
That's it.
-他是建筑承包商  -是的
- He's a contractor? - Yeah.
他这么说的吗
That's what he said?
阿米莉亚  我很好奇
Amelia. I'm just curious.
你这种博倒众生的女人
You are the kind of woman who can get any guy she wants.
怎么看中了维克多·纳沃斯基
Why Viktor Navorski?
你这种男人是永远不会懂的
That's something a guy like you could never understand.
我想你又误机了
I guess you missed your flight again.
也可能是你选的旅行社太差了
Or maybe you have a bad travel agent.
请坐  请坐
Please. Sit.
没关系的  维克多  人都会撒谎
It's okay, Viktor. All men lie.
至少你还不善于撒谎
At least you're not very good at it.
我没有撒谎
I did not lie.
你跟我说你是耽搁在机场的
You told me you were delayed.
可你没说已经耽搁九个月了
You never said it was for nine months.
也许你只看你想看见的
Maybe you see the man the way you want see the man.
那我看见的是什么  你到底是谁
So, what am I seeing? Who are you?
-我...  -被拒绝了吗
- I... - Unacceptable?
是  是
Yes. Yes.
你想知道最有意思的是什么吗
You want to hear the funny part?
我和他分手了
I broke up with him.
我来这儿就是为了告诉你
I was coming here to tell you
他已经不在我的生活里了
he's out of my life.
我自由了  我实在厌倦了等待
I'm free. I got tired of waiting.
至少这一点我们是一样的
At least we have that in common.
阿米莉亚  你知道拿破仑打下巴伐利亚后
Amelia, you know what Napoleon give to Josephine
给了约瑟芬什么吗
when he win Bavaria?
不知道
No.
我告诉你
I show you.
来
Please.
请坐
Sit. Please.
那就是拿破仑给约瑟芬的礼物
That was gift. Napoleon to Josephine.
一千座喷泉
One thousand fountains.
你为我做的吗
You built this for me?
请坐  别弄湿了衣服
Please. Sit. Don't get wet.
拜托啊
Come on.
不好使了
It no work.
应该喷水的  很粗的水柱喷到天花板
It should shoot, big water up to ceiling.
实话告诉我
Just tell me the truth.
你是精神有问题吗
Did you escape from an institution?
你犯了罪吗
Are you a criminal?
你住在这儿  维克多
You're living here, Viktor.
住在67号登机口  我只是想知道为什么
You're living at Gate 67. I just want to know why.
在这儿了  我给你看
Here. I show you.
我父亲
My father.
维克多  别说你父亲在这个罐子里
Viktor, please tell me your father isn't in that peanut can.
这里是爵士乐
This is jazz.
我父亲  迪米塔·阿森诺夫·纳沃斯基
My father, Dimitar Asenov Navorski,
1958年在匈牙利的报纸上看到了这张照片
see this photograph in Hungarian newspaper, 1958.
他说这照片他看了七天
He say he look at photograph for seven days.
周一  周二  周三...
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday...
他们是谁
Who are they?
贝西公爵  迪兹·吉莱斯皮
Count Basie, Dizzy Gillespie,
均为著名爵士音乐家
塞隆尼斯·孟克  桑尼·罗林斯
Thelonious Monk, Sonny Rollins,
亚特·布雷基  马克思·卡明斯基
Art Blakey, Max Kaminsky.
一共57人
57 of them all together.
看了七天之后
After looking at photograph for seven days,
我爸爸有了个想法
my father has idea.
他开始给那些俱乐部写信
He begin to write letters to club,
飞毛腿  史努奇的超级碗什么的
Lickety Split, Snookie's Sugar Bowl.
他拜托修女用英文帮他写信
He ask the nuns to write English.
写了上百封
Hundreds letters.
然后他等了又等
And then he wait.
日复一日  年复一年
He wait month, week, year.
等了40年
My father wait 40 year.
他们都签了名字
And they all sign names.
一个跟着一个
One by one.
把签名寄给了我父亲
They all write their name and send it to my father.
只差一个人
All but not one.
本尼·戈尔森
Benny Golson.
萨克斯手
Saxophone.
我父亲没等到本尼·戈尔森寄来签名
My father die before Benny Golson write his name
就去世了
and send to my father.
于是我向他做出了承诺
So I make him promise.
我会遵守这一承诺
I keep promise.
我向他承诺
I promise I will go New York,
我会去纽约找本尼·戈尔森
find Benny Golson,
拿到他的签名  放进这个罐子
have him write name to put in can.
你一直住在这儿
And you've been living here all this time
就是为了帮你爸爸完成心愿吗
so you could do this for your father?
现在看也许是他在帮我
Maybe I think he do it for me.
你说你一直在等待
You say you are waiting for something.
我想对你说  "是的  我们都在等"
And I say to you, "Yes, yes. We all wait."
你在等什么
What are you waiting for?
你  我等的是你
You. I wait for you.
怎么了
What?
战争结束了
The war is over.
卡科吉亚实现和平
右翼发动军事政变
The right wing military coup
迫使瓦格巴金总统下台
that ousted President Vagobagin...
好了  请大家举起手中的酒杯
All right, everybody. Come on. Let's raise your glasses.
为我的朋友"山羊"维克多干杯
Let's have a toast to my friend, Viktor "The Goat."
祝愿他再也不会失去自己的祖国
May he never lose his country again.
卡科吉亚
Krakozhia.
阿米莉亚  你来的真早
Amelia. You here early.
你好  阿米莉亚  你看
Hello. Amelia, look.
和平  和平  快来  快来
Peace. Peace. The war. The war. Please come. Come.
你看  战争  卡科吉亚战争结束了
See, the war, the war Krakozhia is over.
我们和平了  战争结束了
Peace. The war is over.
-你知道我那个朋友吗  -哪个
- You know my friend? - Yes?
-华盛顿那个  -知道
- He was in Washington. - Yes.
他人脉很广  你看
He has a lot of connections. Here.
维克多  这是一张通行证
It's a pass, Viktor.
一日紧急签证  上面有你的名字
A one-day travel emergency visa with your name on it.
-什么  签证  -是的
- Wha... Visa? - Yes.
-你朋友给的  -是的
- From your friend? - Yeah.
去纽约吧
Just go to New York,
拿到最后一张签名  放进罐子里
find that last name and put it in the can.
-让我去纽约  -没错
- I go New York? - Yes.
我能去纽约啦
I go New York!
阿米莉亚  你和我一起吧
Amelia, you come with.
我们一起去纽约
You come with me to New York.
你朋友帮我弄的吗  他为什么帮我
Your friend do this for me? Why he do this for me?
他是在帮我
He did it for me.
我告诉过你  不要接近我
I told you to stay away from me,
维克多  但是你不明白
Viktor. But you didn't understand.
你觉得你是有点糊涂了
I think you were confused.
不  一切都让我感到糊涂
No, I confused about everything.
我才没有糊涂  对这件事没有
I not confused... Not this. Not this.
抱歉  我要迟到了
I'm sorry. I'm running late.
阿米莉亚  你为什么要走  为什么
Amelia. Why you go? Why you go?
你知道拿破仑给约瑟芬的
You know what Napoleon gave Josephine
新婚礼物是什么吗
as a wedding present?
是一个金色的挂坠盒
It was a gold locket.
他在里面刻了字
And on the inside, he made an inscription.
"命运"
"Destiny."
命运
Destiny.
卡科吉亚人举行庆祝
街头小巷和酒吧
Rejoice in the streets
洋溢在喜悦中
as well as in their local taverns.
远处
In the distance,
卡科吉亚国旗在国会大厦上空飘扬
the Krakozhian flag waved goodbye
向战争告别
from high atop the parliament buildings.
这清楚地标志着...
It is a clear sign of the power...
-嘿  宝贝  -嗨
- Hey, baby. - Hi.
我好想你
I missed you.
走吧
Come on.
下一位
Next.
维克多
Viktor.
你好  多洛莉丝  我今天怎么样
Hello, Dolores. How I am today?
看看这个
What do you have here?
不行  没签字
Oh, no. It's not signed.
什么
What?
这个是一日紧急签证
This is a one-day emergency travel visa.
为了证明其真实性
To validate authenticity,
上面必须要有监管人员的签字
it needs to be signed by the supervising officer.
迪克逊吗
Dixon?
是的
Yes.
迪克逊
Dixon.
我们国家的战争已经结束了
The war in my country is over.
是啊  我知道  恭喜
Yeah. I know. Congratulations.
这很奇怪  是不是  维克多
It's strange, isn't it, Viktor?
你为一件事情等待了很长时间
When you wait so long for one thing?
只需一瞬间就实现了
One tiny moment.
今天我也经历了那样的瞬间
I had that moment today, too.
看见这个徽章了吗
You see this badge?
这说明我已经是
This badge means that
海关与边防局的代理外勤专员了
I was made CBP Field Commissioner.
还说明我全权控制
It means that my authority
本机场的安全情况
over the security of this airport is absolute.
这是你的机票和护照
Your ticket and your passport.
你该回家了
It's time for you to go home.
韦林长官  请带纳沃斯基先生去候机楼
Officer Waylin, please show Mr. Navorski into the terminal
不要让他误了飞机
and make sure he does not miss his flight.
再见了  维克多  祝你好运
Goodbye, Viktor, and good luck.
我想去纽约
I think I want go New York City.
别过分  维克多
Don't make this difficult, Viktor.
我不再是"被拒绝的"了
I no more "Unacceptable."
-我说了  到此为止  -我要去纽约
- I told you this is over. - I go New York.
你确定你要那样做吗
Are you sure you want to do that?
我要去纽约  立刻
I go New York City now.
作为外勤专员
Part of my job as a field commissioner
我还负责清理害群之马
is to get rid of undesirables,
还真不少呢
and there are quite a few.
看看他  乔·莫洛伊
Like this guy, Joe Mulroy.
你应该认识他
I think you know him.
他在这工作20年了
Joe's been here for 20 years,
但却在下班后聚众赌博
but it turns out he's been running an after-hour poker game.
还携带酒和大麻
Bringing in liquor and marijuana.
这可怜虫马上就要没有退休金了
Poor guy's going to lose his pension.
他还有几个孩子呢
And I think he has kids, too.
还有这个人
And then there's this guy,
恩里克·克鲁兹  你应该也认识吧
Enrique Cruz. I think you also know Enrique.
恩里克纵容别人进入
Enrique, it turns out,
食品准备工作区
has been letting people into the food preparation area.
造成了严重的安全隐患
That's a major security breach.
这个可怜虫啊  好像刚结婚呢
The poor guy, I think he's a newlywed.
可我还是得让他走人
But I'm going to have to let him go.
还有这个叫古普塔·拉简的
And then there's Gupta Rajan.
清洁工
He's a janitor.
1979年他居然在印度袭击了一名警官
But as it turns out he's wanted for assaulting a police officer
被警方通缉
back in India in 1979.
所以我得把他驱逐出境
I'll have to deport him.
我会回家的
I will go home.
-抱歉  你说什么  -我会回家的
- I'm sorry. What did you say? - I will go home.
别刁难他们  我就回去
Leave them alone. I will go.
-今天  -是的
- Today. - Yes.
如果你赶不上那班飞机
If you don't get on that plane, Viktor,
他们就都得滚蛋
they're all gone.
-明白吗  -明白  明白
- Do you understand? - Yes. Yes. Yes.
好  很好
Okay. Good.
出发
真不敢相信
I don't believe you.
维克多  你不必这样的
Viktor, you don't have to do this.
你要和他们斗
You can fight these guys, OK?
我们会帮助你的
We'll help you.
维克多  拜托了  我欠你的太多了
Viktor, come on. I owe you so much.
就让我帮帮你吧
Please let me help you.
维克多  听他的吧
Viktor, listen to him,
朋友不会骗你的
this is your friend talking.
我们都是你的朋友  现在就是你的家人
We're all your friends. We're your family now.
古普塔
Gupta.
再见了
Goodbye.
你想骗我们吗
You try to fool us.
你让我们相信你会走出去
You make us to think you would walk out this door,
相信你会和他们斗
that you will fight with them.
可你为什么不斗争呢
Why don't you fight?
战争结束了
The war is over.
那你走吧  快走开
Then go. Get lost.
滚回家去吧  告诉他们你没做到
Get lost. Go home and tell them you never made it.
你离美国就这么远了
You come this close to America,
可你连迈这一步的勇气都没有
but you don't have the courage to go from here to here.
你这个懦夫
You are a coward.
飞机要起飞了
The plane is on time.
你这个懦夫
You are a coward.
You are a coward!
你真让我恶心
You make me sick!
你怎么了  兄弟  淡定点
What's wrong with you, man? Settle down.
人们都在看  像我怎么着了似的
Got people looking all around, looking at me like I'm...
看着我
Look at me.
拜托  看着我
Come on, look at me.
有些事情你应该知道
There's something you should know.
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
来自卡科吉亚的
United Airlines Flight 865
美联航865次航班已经着陆
from Krakozhia has landed
正驶向登机口
and is now taxiing to the gate.
乘坐866次航班
For those passengers holding tickets
前往卡科吉亚的旅客
for Flight 866 to Krakozhia,
请准备登机
we expect departure to be on schedule.
古普塔
Gupta.
我要回家了
I am going home.
快走吧
Get lost.
请各位旅客注意
Your attention, please.
前往卡科吉亚的866次航班延误
Flight 866 to Krakozhia will be delayed
起飞时间待定
until further notice.
各位有预约吗
Do you have an appointment?
谁能告诉我下面他妈的怎么了
Somebody tell me what the hell is going on down there.
我们都一直支持你
We're right behind you.
维克多走了
Viktor's leaving.
莫妮卡  维克多走了
Monica, Viktor's leaving.
我知道  他要回家了
I know. He's going home.
他向出口走呢  要进纽约了
He's going for the front door, out to the city.
什么  我的天...
What? Oh, my...
维克多  别忘了我们
Viktor. Remember us.
我是"探索"商店的
Hey, on behalf of the Discovery Store,
我想送你这个
I want to give you this.
它代表着好运
It's good luck.
这数码相机送给卡莎表妹
A digital camera for Cousin Katia.
我不知道你要去哪
I don't know where you're going, Viktor,
但这个能让你的脚暖和
but these will keep your feet warm
陪您到达目的地
and help you get there.
-各就各位了吗  -我们都在
- Everybody in position? - We're here.
那就好  看住大门
That's it. Secure the door.
对不住了   维克多
Sorry, Viktor.
乔奇  逮捕他
Take him, Judge.
维克多  请留步  放松点
Hold it, Viktor. Take it easy.
你看见那些大门了吗
You see those doors?
那些是纽约市的入口
Those are the entry doors to New York City.
是美利坚合众国的入口
To the United States of America.
转过去
Turn around.
外面下雪了  你会需要它的
It's snowing in the city, and you're going to need that.
祝你好运
Good luck.
不是吧  不是吧  不是吧
Oh, no. Oh, no. Oh, no...
我会想你的
I'm going to miss you.
不管以后去哪  可别再被困住了
Try not to get stuck wherever you're going.
抓住他  抓住他
Arrest him! Arrest him!
该死的
God damn it!
出租车
Taxi.
谢谢你
Thank you.
到哪
Where you go?
莱克星顿161号
161 Lexington.
麻烦您走范威克高速公路  过皇后大桥
Please take Van Wyck Expressway to Queensboro Bridge.
比走皇后区快速路要快
It's faster than BQE.
你从哪来
Where you from?
卡科吉亚  维克多·纳沃斯基
Krakozhia. Viktor Navorski.
我叫戈兰  阿尔巴尼亚人
I'm Goran. Albania.
-你什么时候来纽约的  -周四
- When do you come to New York? - Thursday.
你是让我们封锁南边的出口
You want us to block the south exit
检查每辆汽车吗
and have AP sweep every vehicle?
长官
Sir?
来自东京的530次航班已经降落了
530 from Tokyo just landed.
停机坪上停着两架飞机
Got two planes on the tarmac.
巴塞罗那的航班也要到了
Barcelona on approach.
这才刚入夜
The night is young,
还有1500名乘客等着我们呢
and 1,500 people are headed our way.
大家都进去吧  进去吧
Everybody inside. Everybody inside.
-走吧  -我们走
- Come on. - Let's go.
走吧
Let's go.
您要入住吗  先生
Are you checking in, sir?
不不  我不是要入住的
No, no. I don't check in.
请问怎么去这个地方
I want to go to this place, please.
大堂酒吧就在拐角那儿
The lobby lounge is right around the corner, Sir.
那里每晚都提供打折的酒水
They have happy hour specials
还有现场音乐表演
and live music every night.
你喜欢爵士乐吗
Do you like jazz?
我们来演奏杀手乔吧
Let's do Killer Joe.
昨晚很受欢迎  再演一次
It worked all right last night, so I'll try.
-什么事  -你是本尼·戈尔森吗
- Yes? - You are Benny Golson?
是啊  我是
Yeah. Yes, I am.
本尼·戈尔森
Benny Golson,
我叫维克多·纳沃斯基  我来自卡科吉亚
I am Viktor Navorski. I am from Krakozhia.
我的父亲迪米塔·阿森诺夫·纳沃斯基
My father, Dimitar Asenov Navorski,
是您的铁杆歌迷
was great, great fan of your music.
爵士乐迷啊  太棒了
Oh, a jazz fan. Fantastic.
请问您能签个名吗
Would you sign your name, please?
一会儿签行吗  我们马上要表演了
Oh. Can I do it a little later? We have to get started now.
-马上就好  -我等您
- Just a minute. - I will wait.
好的
Okay.
爵士乐的传奇
本尼·戈尔森
出租车  出租车
Taxi. Taxi.
你要去哪
Where you want to go?
我要回家了
I am going home.